Roopak TJ | Curriculum Vitae

Room2, 5 Maroona Road, Carnegie - VIC-3163

□ +61-497522844 • ✓ mailstorpk@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/roopak-tj-0697179b/

Experienced in Big Data analytics and Apache Crunch Pipeline implementation. Strong engineering background with an Undergraduate degree in Computer Science and Engineering. Now pursuing a Masters degree in Data Science from Monash University, Australia.

Education

Academic Qualifications.....

Master of Data Science, Caulfield campus

Monash University

Post Gradguate Degree,

2018-Present

Amrita School of Engineering, Amritapuri campus

Amrita University

Bachelor of Technology, Computer Science and Engineering, CGPA: 8.6

2012-2016

Kendriya Vidyalaya Bhusawal, Maharashtra

Higher Secondary Education

, Cental Board of Secondary Education, 12th Grade 84.6 percentage

2011

Kendriya Vidyalaya Air Force Station, Nasik, Maharashtra

Secondary Education

2009

Cental Board of Secondary Education, 10th Grade

92 percentage

Work Experience

NJM Group Melbourne

Wordpress Developer

November 2018

Worked as Wordpress Developer in NJM Group, Melbourne Australia and was responsible for creating, maintaining and updating sites in Wordpress

Cerner HealthCare Solutions

Banglore

Software Engineer

July 2016-July 2018

Worked as Software Engineer in Cerner Healthcare Solutions Pvt. Ltd. Responsible for data analysis, design fabrication and end to end Apache Crunch Pipeline implementation for Revenue Cycle Analytics Project. Team involved in creating different reports for revenue cycle of a hospital using Big Data and Hadoop technologies

Cerner HealthCare Solutions

Banglore

Seasonal Intern

January 2016- July 2016

Successfully completed final year undergraduate project as a part of Internship in Cerner HealthCare Solutions. The project included the implementation of an ETL job from scratch using Map Reduce framework of Apache Hadoop and normalize the data into noSQL HBase tables

Technical and Personal skills

- o **Programming Languages:** Java, Python, C++.
- o Big Data skills Map Reduce, Hadoop, Apache Crunch, Vertica DBveaver, Access, Visio
- o Office Suite skills PowerPoint, Word, Data analysis and Visualization using Excel
- o Platforms: GNU/Linux (Ubuntu), Windows, Mac OS.
- Version Control System : Git
- Web Development : HTML, CSS, PHP, Wordpress
- Platform/IDE: Eclipse/Intellije IDE for Java projects, Sublime Text, Jupyter notebook/Pycharm for Python,PostgreSQL
- o Industry Software Skills: Issue tracking products: Jira and Bugzilla.

Collabrative code review software: Crucible

Continuous Integration and development software: Jenkins

o General Business Skills: Good presentation skills, Agile team working experience.

Publications and Achievements

Rated as Highly Valued Associate
 SEPT 2016: Rated as highly valued associated in Cerner after their first appraisal cycle.

Cerner NOTT Award 'Award for Excellence in Cerner'

JULY 2016: Awarded with NOTT for the exceptional work on the end to end implementation of an Apache Cruch pipeline as per Client requirement.

- Article published in Magazine Open Source For You
 JULY 2014: Article on "Swapping Space for Linux" got published in the "Open Source for You" Magazine.
- Open Source Contributions Mediawiki and LibreOffice
 JANUARY 2014 onwards: Contributed and fixed bugs in a couple of Open source Organizations like Mediawiki and LibreOffice.
- ACM- ICPC Programming competition
 DECEMBER 2013 onwards: Team was selected for the regional level of ACM ICPC.

Projects

- Sentiment Analysis Tool with Twitter Data using Python: Implemented a Sentiment analysis tool
 with Twitter Data using Python programming language. The script uses packages like tweepy to extract
 tweets, textBlob for identifying the polarity of tweets and matplotlib for graphical representation of the
 public sentiment using Pie-Chart and WordCloud.
- Apache Crunch Pipeline Implementation: Worked on end to end implementation of Apache Crunch pipelines which generated reports and KPI's for the end user. Project also involved validation of client production data using CCL(Cerner Command Line) and SQL scripts
- o Cerner Internship Project: Implementation of ETL jobs to load data from a SQL database, normalise it and populate in a noSQL HBase database using MapReduce jobs. Also involved testing and debugging MapReduce programs using MRunit tests Knowledge of Apache Hadoop, MapReduce, Hbase, SQL, Git, Linux commands and Healthcare terminologies
- o **Custom Detectors for Findbugs**: Findbugs is a static code analysis tool used in Java programming language which has a set of pre-defined rules. Implemented a plugin to add new set of custom rules in 'findbugs', which was specific to the Revenue Cycle Analytics project. Rules included Camel-casing of variables etc

- o Data Structures: Implemented Data Structures like Linked List, Stack, Queue and Binary Search Tree.
- Open Source Projects:
 - 1. Bugs fixed in Mediawiki
 - https://gerrit.wikimedia.org/r//c/107333/
 - https://gerrit.wikimedia.org/r//c/108512/
 - https://gerrit.wikimedia.org/r//c/108326/

Leadership Qualities

- o April 2015: Technical Head "Battle of Whiz", a week long intense programming camp, organized by Codechef, for training School students in basic competitive pro- gramming
- o Nov 2014: Conducted a "Fire and safety awareness campaign" as a part of SSR Project.
- o Oct 2014: Coordinated DebUtsav'14, a Debian Conference conducted in the college.
- Sept 2012-13: Volunteerd for Amma's Birthday Celebrations, an international event which attracts more than 1 lakh people.
- o Vidyut Tech Fest of Amrita:-Played an integral part in Accommodation Resource Department.

Extra Curricular Activities

- o Sept 2014: Represented Computer Science Department in the Department wise Volleyball Tournament.
- o Interested in playing cricket, football, badminton. Represented Com- puter Science Department in Annual Athletic Meet of the College.
- o March 2014: Secured A grade with first position in Amritakalolsavam 14 cartooning competition.
- o March 2015: Secured Third price for Boys Group dance event in Amritakalolsavam 15.

References

- Mrs. Jyothisha Rajesh
 Head of Department,
 Computer Science Engg. Dept,
 Amrita School of Engineering,
- Ph: +91 9447205116

Mr Raju Aralikkati
 Team Lead, Software Architect
 Cerner HealthCare Solutions,

Banglore

Ph: +91 8123657887